<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->

<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">
  <properties>
    <title>Motu Dissemination Server</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Motu Dissemination Server">
		<subsection name="Functionalities">
			<p>Motu is a high efficient and robust Web Application which fills the gap between heterogeneous Data Providers to end users.</p>
			<p>Its key features are:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Motu handles, extracts and transforms oceanographic data through a published interface on the Web;</li>
				<li>Motu has the capacity to process huge volumes of data without service overloading or performance collapse;</li>
				<li>Motu reports and details the activity of its process.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Motu allows the user to download data files though a generic web client (web browser like Internet Explorer 
			or Firefox through the web portal, command line web browser like curl directly on the dissemination unit service).
			Motu is able to connect to a central authentication (capacity at server and client side) and provides advanced 
			transaction accounting logs automatically.</p>
			<p>All the data which can be distributed through Opendap will be read by Motu trough this interface, including then 
			all the gridded data. The data are read through FTP because the data type is not managed by Opendap (non-gridded dataset).</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Standards">
			<p>Motu embraces as much as possible the existing standards to be most compatible and interoperable. 
			The following table enumerates the several standards on which Motu relies on.</p>
			<table>
				<tr>
					<th>Designation</th>
					<th>Standard</th>
					<th>Version</th>
					<th>Organism</th>
					<th>Reference</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Interface</td>
					<td>WPS</td>
					<td>1.0</td>
					<td>OGC</td>
					<td>OpenGIS Implementation Specication #05-007r7</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Interface</td>
					<td>REST</td>
					<td>-</td>
					<td>-</td>
					<td>Fielding, Roy T.; Taylor, Richard N. (2002-05)</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Protocol</td>
					<td>HTTP</td>
					<td>1.1</td>
					<td>ICOC</td>
					<td>RFC-2616</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>Configuration</td>
					<td>XML</td>
					<td>1.1</td>
					<td>W3C</td>
					<td>Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0 (Fifth Edition)</td>
				</tr>
			</table>
			<p>In the near future, Motu will provide the OpenGIS® Web Coverage Service (WCS) protocol, enhanced traceability and monitoring features, 
			and the implementation of several new WPS units like Data Normalization and Data Transformation.</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Libraries used">
			<p>This component is a JEE application based on the following open-source software components (not exhaustive):</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Netcdf library</li>
				<li>Opendap library</li>
				<li>Deegree as the OGC stack for WPS</li>
				<li>Jena and Protégé API for handling ontologies</li>
				<li>Quartz for job scheduling</li>
				<li>Freemarker as the main template engine</li>
			</ul>			
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="System requirements">
			<p><b>Hardware</b></p>
			<p>Even if no detailed hardware prerequisite exits, typical hardware configuration could be the following: 64 bits processor, 4 GB RAM, about 4 GB disk space available.</p>
			<p>Note that Motu can be installed in the same computer as Thredds Data Server.</p>
			<p><b>Software</b></p>
			<p>MOTU is a JEE application to deploy. The installation consists in:</p>
			<ol>
				<li>Installing the JEE pre-requisites</li>
				<li>Installing a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Application_server#Java_application_servers">Java Application Server</a> (like <a href="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Tomcat</a>) for MOTU, configured for <a href="http://www.jasig.org/cas">CAS server</a></li>
				<li>Generate certificate for CAS server dialog</li>
				<li>Install the Motu J2EE application in the webapp directory</li>
			</ol>
			<p>Motu have been tested with Tomcat 6.0 on a linux CentOS release 5.4 (Final), kernel 2.6.18-164.6.1.el5, x86_64.</p>
			<p>The portability of java allows saying that it can be installed on many operating systems.</p>
		</subsection>
		
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
